Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ח. Samech-Chet. And
again, it's a short דף daf in terms of the
גמרא, Gemara, last lots of ר"ן, Ran, and it's also not really
much of a meaty halakhic discussion; it's in some ways very similar
to what we saw yesterday. Yesterday, the question was that the משנה
mishna introduces the idea that when a girl is not yet a
בוגרת, bogeres, she's a נערה, na'arah, or in some cases a case
we even include a case of a קטנה ketanah whose נדר neder
is binding, so she halakhically is considered to be in her father's
house. Even after קידושין, kiddushin, until נישואין, nissu'in, until the father hands
over to the בעל ba'al and there's what was called חופה, chuppah,
נישואין, nissu'in, and so on, she's not only physically, but more importantly
for us halakhically considered to be in her father's house and under
her father's control. Nevertheless, חז"ל Chazal read one of the sections in
the תורה Torah that talks about the husband or the father being
מיפר meifer the נדר, neder, voiding the vow, and it reads it
to be a case where they are both partners in the act
when she's a נערה na'arah and she has קידושין, kiddushin, she's מאורסה,
murasah, נערה מאורסה, na'arah murasah, but in that case we would normally
expect it to be only defined by the father, but חז"ל Chazal
are telling us no, the husband is also part of it. That's
how they read one of the פרשיות parashiyos in the תורה, Torah,
one of the sections in the תורה, Torah, and that the father
and the husband combined annul the vow. And as we also said,
it really is primarily the father, again ironically because the פרשה parasha
of the תורה Torah that they're hinting at really talks primarily about
the husband, but they're saying based on the normal idea that again
this girl before נישואין nissu'in is considered in the father's house, so
it's primarily the father and the relevance of that is two things.
Number one is that it applies to vows that existed prior to
the קידושין, kiddushin, because it really is the father who is fundamentally
being seen as the one who's annulling it.
And number two, we're going to see if she doesn't have a
father, if she's let's say a יתומה, yesomah, orphan, and she has
קידושין, kiddushin, the husband cannot annul the vow. So it really requires
the father; the father is really central. Okay, so now it could
continue and both of those themes we're going to continue today. First,
to wrap up looking at what פסוקים psukim we might get it
from and then to talk about this relationship of the father and
the husband and which one is more sort of the anchor of
it. Okay, top of ס"ח ע"א: Samech-Chet amud aleph: תני דבי רבי
ישמעאל, Tanya devei Rabbi Ishmael, from the house of Rabbi Ishmael taught
the following
ברייתא, braita, בין איש לאשתו בין אב לבתו. Bein ish l'ishto bein
av l'vito. So it says these are the laws about the vows,
בין איש לאשתו bein ish l'ishto between husband and wife, בין אב
לבתו bein av l'vito between a father and his daughter, בנעוריה בית
אביה, b'neureha beis aviha, when she is in her youth in her
father's house. So it already says אב לבתו, av l'vito, why say
בנעוריה בית אביה? b'neureha beis aviha? Well, presumably the פשט pshat of
the פסוק pasuk is that's when it's about the father and the
daughter. When she's not בית אביה, beis aviha, when she's married, then
it's about the husband. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does
with it. מכאן לנערה מאורסה שאביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. Mikan l'na'arah murasah
she'aviha u'va'alah mefirin nedareha.
It works perfect. It reads the פסוק pasuk to tell me that
not either בין איש לאשתו bein ish l'ishto or בין אב לבתו,
bein av l'vito, but there is some case that is both בין
איש לאשתו bein ish l'ishto and בין אב לבתו. bein av l'vito.
And what case is that? בנעוריה בית אביה. B'neureha beis aviha. When
she's a נערה na'arah in her father's house, but there is also
a husband, there is also a groom, it's a נערה מאורסה. na'arah
murasah. That's how he reads. מכאן לנערה מאורסה שאביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה.
Mikan l'na'arah murasah she'aviha u'va'alah mefirin nedareha. So the גמרא Gemara says
ולתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, v'litana devei Rabbi Ishmael, according to this
תנא, tanna, והיה תהיה לאיש ונדריה עליה, v'hayah tihyeh l'ish v'nedareha aleiha,
what does he do with that section in the תורה? Torah? So
מוקים לה אידך דרבה, mokim lah idach d'Rabbah, for the other teaching
of Rabbah, which we're going to get to in about two דפים,
dafim, and basically it's the double language of והיה תהיה v'hayah tihyeh
where it's a question about that if one groom dies and the
other groom gets married, if the groom dies and then she marries
another groom, what's the father's status between those two marriages? She's still
a נערה, na'arah, she's still in the father's house, there's one groom,
he dies, then there's a period of time, then she marries another
groom. So it reads והיה תהיה לאיש v'hayah tihyeh l'ish to tell
you that the same relationship the father had with her before she
married the first groom is resumed before she marries the second. Okay,
so he has full control over her. Is that sort of clear
what the דרשה drasha is? והיה תהיה v'hayah tihyeh means that there
are going to be two קידושין. kiddushin. So it's reading it as
a case where there was a groom, he died, and another groom,
and it says the father's full control over her before the marriage
to the first groom resumes before the marriage to the second. We'll
see about that in two days. Okay, that's what we do with
it.
ואידך דרבה, v'idach d'Rabbah, the other
teaching of Rabbah. ורבה האי תנא דבי חזקיה דבי רבי ישמעאל מאי
עביד ביה, v'Rabbah hai tanna devei Chizkiyah devei Rabbi Ishmael mai avid
bei, what does he do with this פסוק pasuk בין איש לאשתו
בין אב לבתו? bein ish l'ishto bein av l'vito? So מבעי ליה
לומר שהבעל מיפר נדרים שבינו לבינה, mibayei leih lomar she'haba'al meifer nedarim
shebeino l'veinah, to tell me the very important הלכה, halakhah, what are
the vows that a husband
can annul? Can he annul any vow that his wife... Yes, maybe
his, you know, control over her is absolute. But like, I know,
I mean, but really? Like, does he get to tell her everything
that she can and can't do in the house? Like, what are
the limits, you know, even within this sort of patriarchal society where
the father controls and the husband controls? Is it without any limits?
So חז"ל Chazal see through the תורה Torah that there are two
categories that the husband can annul. One is explicit in the תורה.
Torah. The תורה Torah continuously repeats the idea of לאסור איסר על
נפשה,
le'esor issar al
nafshah, right, to make something
forbidden on themselves. So therefore, that refers to all vows that are
about sort of עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, that are about like afflicting
the, you know, that are a type of a self-affliction that you're
denying something to yourself, making something forbidden yourself. So the other, or
the other way for actually that's phrased in the תורה: Torah: איסר
לענות נפש, issar le'annot nefesh, right? איש כי ידור נדר לענות נפש
אשה כי תדור נדר? ish ki yidor neder le'annot nefesh ishah ki
tiddor neder? So for that some type of affliction of the soul,
denial of the soul, right, the same thing we have by יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, תענו את נפשותיכם. te'anu et nafshoteichem. All right, but
the other thing is, let's say it's a vow that impacts their
dynamics as husband and wife that isn't really directly about some type
of a self-denial. Now what exactly that will be we'll see, but
עינוי נפש inuy nefesh might have a, you know, might have a
threshold. Let's say she basically takes a vow that says, I don't
know, all makeup is forbidden to me, okay, or all certain types
of dresses are forbidden to me. And that's not really עינוי נפש,
inuy nefesh, עינוי נפש inuy nefesh has a certain threshold to it,
but that really, like, you know, he really wants her to be
wearing those dresses and he feels that somehow, I don't know, it's
impacting their, you know, their dynamics or his attraction to her or
something of that nature. Would he be able to annul that vow?
So that we learn from the category of
בין איש לאשתו, bein ish l'ishto, דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim she'beino l'veinah,
things that directly impact their relationship. Okay, so those are the two
categories: עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and דברים שבינו לבינה. devarim she'beino l'veinah.
So בין איש לאשתו bein ish l'ishto tells us that there's a
second category that he can annul. Now here's an interesting question. That
is about the husband.
What's about the father? And is the father, you know, what would
you say? Now there are different types of things that might impact
the father, the daughter, and their relationship, right? Not of a sort
of romantic attraction nature, but other types of things that you could
say. So would you say that it's two categories, עינוי נפש inuy
nefesh and דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim she'beino l'veinah, or would you say
that maybe the father's control over his daughter—and let's remember, she's all
of twelve, right, up to twelve or twelve and a half according
to חז"ל, Chazal, right—maybe that is absolute? So that actually is a
מחלוקת ראשונים, machloket Rishonim, whether the same limits apply, categories apply to
the father. If you take a look at the ר"ן, Ran, ר"ן
Ran says like this.
He says, let's start like five lines before the line get wide,
he says, or the widest lines of the ר"ן, Ran, five lines
before that starts with עינוי. inuy. He says: וגרסינן נמי בירושלמי כל
נדר וכל שבועת איסר לענות נפש אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו אין לי
אלא נדרים שיש בהן עינוי נפש דברים שבינו לבינה מנין בין איש
לאשתו.
ve'garsinan nami b'Yerushalmi kol neder v'chol
shevuat issar le'annot nefesh ishah yekimennu ve'ishah yeferennu ein li ella nedarim
she'yesh bahen inuy nefesh devarim she'beino l'veinah minayin bein ish l'ishto. Okay,
so that's so far what we sort of said. Okay, that's about
the husband. הדא דבירושלמי, hada d'viYerushalmi,
that's as far as the husband is concerned. ואב מנין? ve'av minayin?
How about the father? מה הבעל הוא מיפר בדברים שיש בהן עינוי
נפש דברים שבינו לבינה אף האב אינו מיפר אלא בדברים שיש בהן
עינוי נפש דברים שבינו לבינה.
ma haba'al hu meifer b'devarim she'yesh bahen inuy nefesh devarim she'beino l'veinah
af ha'av eino meifer ella b'devarim she'yesh bahen inuy nefesh
devarim she'beino l'veinah. Okay, pretty explicit, right? The same two categories of
the husband—עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and things that apply to the, that
affect the two, the relationship of the two of them—the same is
true about the father. וזה שלא כדברי הרמב"ם ז"ל שכתב שאב מיפר
כל נדרי בתו. v'zeh shelo k'divrei haRambam zal she'katav she'av meifer kol
nidrei bito. Okay,
but the רמב"ם Rambam says—the רמב"ם Rambam says
categorical—it's not explicit in the בבלי Bavli that this is limited to,
that this limit applies to the father, the רמב"ם Rambam says the
father actually it is categorical. Okay, very interesting, right? And these things
are presumably also not just questions about הלכות נדרים, hilchot nedarim, but
to some degree one would expect, I mean, looking to reflect the
question of, right, the degree of control that we are assuming exists
between husband and wife and between father and daughter. Yes. With this
or the—excuse me—the later פסוק pasuk to
limit this be a form of a
כלל ופרט? klal u'prat? No,
there's not a כלל, klal, there's two פרטי. prati. One פרט prat
is לענות נפש le'annot nefesh and the other is בין איש לאשתו.
bein ish l'ishto. So those are two פרטי. prati. Not
a כלל ופרט. klal u'prat.
Each one is adding a new category. Okay, yes.
Does this require to physically reside in her father's home? I mean,
suppose she's living, never really comes back home between marriages? Presumably no.
The whole idea about being בבית אביה, be'veit aviha, that she's not
even living with her father at all. Let's say, I don't know,
the father and her mother got divorced and she's living with her
mother. הלכתית, halachit, like she still, what the case might be, she's
still הלכתית halachit considered living with her father. Or she's in boarding
school, right, halfway around the world. הלכתית, halachit, the point is a
conceptual בבית אביה. be'veit aviha. Okay, so and that's exactly the point
of the דרשה derashah is that even
though... if there was a נישואין nisuin and the husband died, even
if she was a קטנה, katana, she'd be considered to be an
emancipated minor, a יתומה דחיי אביה, yesoma dechaye aviha, because after נישואין,
nisuin,
actually fully left her father's control, fully in her husband's, now there's
no husband, now she's fully on her own. The whole חידוש chidush
of הידיעה hayediya is that קידושין kidushin doesn't do that. קידושין kidushin
never really takes her out of her father's control. So once the
guy died, she reverts to, you know, then only the father's in
the picture. Okay. So now we continue with the following, now we're
going to get, thank you, now we're going to get to a
הלכה halacha question, which seemed like it's going to lead to some
interesting analysis, but what it's really going to turn to is again
like a little bit of a challenge from a ברייתא braisa that
we're going to have to parse. So let's take a look. איבעיא
להו, ibaia lehu, they raise the following question: בעל מיגז גייז או
מיקלש קליש? baal megez gayiz o miklesh kalesh? Does the husband, when
he does the הפרה hafarah and in theory this could be asked
also when the father does the הפרה, hafarah, but in this partnership,
what's the nature of the partnership? Does each one cut off half?
He cuts off half and then the other guy cuts off his
half? Okay. And so when one does the הפרה, hafarah, you're only
left with half of the נדר. neder. So each act of הפרה
hafarah does something.
Each one cuts off half, but if you did one and not
the other then at least something would have been accomplished. Okay. What
the implications of that we'll see. Or that's מיגז גייז, megez gayiz,
cut it off. Or מיקלש קליש. miklesh kalesh. It weakens it, but
the whole thing is still there just in a weaker state. It's
like does it cut it widthwise or lengthwise if you want to
think about it that way, right? There's the whole thing there in
a weaker state or only half of it is there. So the
גמרא gemara says: היכי קמיבעיא להו, heichi kamibaia lehu,
what would be the case, the application of this? כגון דנדרה מתרי
זיתין, kegon denadra mitrei zeisin, like she made a vow not to
eat two olives worth of something, or let's even just say two
olives, okay. ושמע ארוס והפר לה, veshama arus veheifer la, and the
ארוס arus heard and he annulled it. ואכלתהון, veachaltinhun, and she ate
both of the olives. אי אמרינן מיגז גייז, ei amrinan megez gayiz,
if he at least cut off half, so לקיא, lakya, she would
get lashed because if he cut off half, that means that now
she will now, if he cut off half, she's not forbidden from
both olives now. It's not that she said I can't eat two
olives worth of something. I can't eat this olive and this olive.
These two olives right here I won't eat. Okay. So if he
cut off half, now he really only made her forbidden in one
olive. We don't know which it was, but she's now only forbidden
in one of those two olives, not in both of them. Okay.
So then she would get מלקות malkos because she ate both of
them. If she only ate one it would be a ספק. safek.
But okay, that would be that case. Okay, but אי אמרינן מיקלש
קליש, ei amrinan miklesh kalesh, but if he weakened it, איסורא בעלמא
הוא, issura bealma hu, then yes she violated but it no longer
has the same weight, so it would no longer be deserving of
מלקות. malkos. The prohibition would have somehow been weakened. Now of course
it's so funny because yeah go ahead. Okay I was just like
who says it does anything? You need both people to do it.
You know it's sort of like I don't know like like this
image just popped into my head. You know the thing
about like the nuclear bomb when you need everybody
to put their key in before you can push it? If you
don't have both keys in, nothing happens, right? So who says each
you says that any one of them by itself does anything? Oh
that's something too.
Okay yeah well when when if I remember right when it comes
to things like like רוב, rov, right? If you have if you
eat both all the pieces of all ten pieces of meat and
you know one of them was from the non-kosher place, then you
can eat but they're all kosher.
Right that's when you have ביטול. bitul. But over here it's like
one and one you know? That's true if you have three and
one though right?
I mean when I eat this olive how do I know?
No that's if you pop them both in your mouth at the
same time. That would be more like חטיפה chatifa stuffing? Right, but
this wouldn't be the case you wouldn't have חטיפה chatifa stuffing you
pop them both in your mouth at the same time. But still
okay that's a gross question. It assumes that one הפרה hafarah has
some independent effect. It's the same question.
Do you have what isn't the case you have ten pieces of
ten steaks and you know one of them came from one of
them came from the non-kosher...
oh that's כל דפריש מרובא
פריש.
kol daparish
meruba parish. But again that's when there's a רוב. rov. There's not
a רוב rov here, it's equal balanced and it's not דפריש, deparish,
you're putting both of them in your mouth. So no that's not
the
way... I don't know anyway. I still think the problem is like
who says who says half of it does anything? All right anyway
let's take a look. So now the גמרא gemara says like this.
So מאי? mai? So the problem is that the גמרא gemara is
not going to conceptually analyze this. It's going to just bring one
piece of evidence as a proof and it's going to and it's
going to say okay that proves it. It's going to bring one
ברייתא. braisa. Now it would be nice if the ברייתא braisa said
it directly but it's going to be a very complicated ברייתא. braisa.
But at the end of the ברייתא braisa the גמרא gemara is
going to conclude its question. So let's take a look. תא שמע:
ta shema: אימתי
אמרו מת הבעל נתרוקנה רשות לאב? eimasay amru meis habaal nisrokna reshus
laav? Okay. Now here is the statement of the that this ברייתא
braisa is dealing with. Okay. Oh
gosh for some reason I haven't used this for a while here.
Great. It's oh God, first time using this in a while
here. Great. נדרוך Nidrok נדרוכנה nidroknah רשות לאב rishut la'av
ומת האב
ולא נדרוכנה רשות לבעל. u-met ha-av ve-lo
nidroknah rishut
la-baal. Basically this is the statement that the ברייתא Braitah is now
going to unpack, which means the husband dies, he empties out his
right to the father. The father dies, his rights are not transferred
or emptied to the husband. Which basically is another way of saying
the father is the anchor. Okay, the father, which is what we've
been saying, the father is the anchor in the annulling, in the
הפרה. hafara. So if the husband dies, then the father assumes total
control. And he can annul it even without the husband. But if
the father dies, right, the husband is not the one who's really
doing the הפרה. hafara. So if the husband isn't the anchor and
the father dies, then she's not going to be able to get
her vow annulled, okay? His rights, his powers, whatever, do not get
transferred to the husband. All right, that's the conceptual point. And now
let's read it in the ברייתא. Braitah. Okay, תא שמע. Tashma. אימתי
אמרו מת הבעל נדרוכנה רשות לאב? Eimatai amru met ha-baal nidroknah rishut
la'av?
When the husband dies, the father gains full control. Okay, his rights
are transferred fully to the father because again, the father is the
anchor. בזמן שלא שמע הבעל קודם שימות. Bizman she-lo shama ha-baal kodem
she-yamut.
So before the husband dies, she took a vow before the husband
dies, and he didn't hear about it. או O or,
ששמע ושתק she-shama ve-shatak and he didn't do anything. Now if he
was שתק, shatak, being silent for 24 hours is basically like a
קיום. kiyum. So we're going to see in a minute that he
died within 24 hours. So he did not effectively do a קיום.
kiyum. Okay, so scenario number two is he heard, he didn't hear,
or he heard and died within 24 hours. או ששמע והפר O
she-shama ve-hefer or he actively was מפר. mefer. In all those cases,
he either did nothing or didn't do anything that was a problem,
right? So as long as you don't do anything or you don't
do anything problematic, we're good. Then you're going to die, then the
father will be able to take care of the situation. Okay, או
ששמע והפר, o she-shama ve-hefer, ששמע ושתק, she-shama ve-shatak, או ששמע והפר
o she-shama ve-hefer ומת בו ביום. u-met bo bayom.
He died on that day. It doesn't have to be the day
he did הפרה hafara because once he did הפרה hafara great, but
he died on the day that he heard and was מפר. mefer.
So he didn't go 24 hours with being silent, okay? So in
those three scenarios, זו היא ששנינו מת הבעל נדרוכנה רשות לאב. zo
hi she-shananu met ha-baal nidroknah rishut la'av. Okay, three easy scenarios where
he didn't
either do anything or didn't do anything wrong, all right? He didn't
hear about it, or he heard about it and did a הפרה,
hafara, thank you very much, wasn't necessary, but thank you, or he
heard about it and died within 24 hours so he didn't have
a chance that his silence should become like קיום. kiyum. So you
didn't do anything wrong, you're dead, now the father will take care
of it. אבל Aval but, אם שמע וקיים, im shama ve-kiyem,
there are two bad things he can do. Okay, he heard about
it and he did a קיום. kiyum. או ששמע ושתק ומת ביום
של אחריו O she-shama ve-shatak u-met beyom shel achario or he was
silent for 24 hours after hearing about it, which is effectively a
קיום, kiyum, right? It's like a pocket veto, it's the opposite, it's
a pocket קיום. kiyum. Okay, he said nothing, so he basically was
מקיים mekayem it. In that case, אין יכול להפר. ein yachol le-hafer.
And then he dies, then the father isn't able to because he
put a stop to it, right? So when the husband by the
husband stopping it, you don't need the husband's power to annul, but
if he was מקיים mekayem it before he died, then then it's
a done deal. All right, that's very really that's very simple, all
right? Husband dies, the father can annul it, provided that the husband
did not do something to be מקיים mekayem it before he died.
Okay, now, that's scenario number one, where the husband dies and the
father can annul. Now we're going to do the reverse. The father
dies and the husband cannot annul. שמע אביה והפר לה. Shama avia
ve-hefer lah.
Let's say the father heard and he even did an active הפרה.
hafara. He did everything he should have done, an active הפרה. hafara.
ולא הספיק בעל לשמוע עד שמת האב. Ve-lo hispik baal lishmoa ad
she-met ha-av.
And the husband didn't even hear about it until the father died.
Now there's a reason for this long run, it's to just explain
like why some of these cases, where the חידוש chidush is in
some of these cases. So the ר"ן Ran says the חידוש chidush
here is that I might think that if the husband didn't even
hear about it until the father died, that makes the father's הפרה
hafara even more powerful, right? The husband isn't even in the picture
right now. The only person in the picture is the father. Anyway
we already know that the husband is pretty tangential. Okay, and the
father heard about it and was מפר. mefer. So now I would
think like, okay, it's completely הופר hufar 99%, and now after the
father dies, the husband only comes into the picture after the father
dies, so maybe now he's there by himself, it was all basically
done, he can maybe finish up the job. ולא הספיק בעל לשמוע
עד שמת האב, Ve-lo hispik baal lishmoa ad she-met ha-av, still he
can't do anything, זו היא ששנינו מת האב לא נדרוכנה. zo hi
she-shananu met ha-av lo nidroknah. just with the בעל. baal.
Okay, doesn't matter. No matter what the father did and no matter
how precisely the husband came into the picture at exactly what time,
if the father, the father is the anchor.
And if the father, and therefore, if it's not enough that he
did his הפרה, hafara, it's without him together with the husband, right,
the husband cannot finish the job. The father has to be there
around for the end of the הפרה hafara to work. Okay? So
if the father did everything and then died, it doesn't matter, the
husband can't finish that job. Okay, right? It's pretty straightforward. I mean,
again, this diagram is pretty intimidating, but it's pretty straightforward. Okay, as
long as the husband doesn't make problems and he dies, the father
can take care of it. Okay, because it's all the father. If
the father, even if the father did everything and he could have
died, he was מיפר, meifer, etc., and then he died, the husband
can't take care of what's left without the father being there.
All right, now, what happens to a new vow after the father
dies? If she makes a new vow?
So then also the husband can't do anything.
Until there's נישואין. nissuin.
Until there's נישואין, nissuin, yeah. I said that before. I guess now
it's kicking in.
Can he do it retroactively once they're on the first day of
נישואין? nissuin?
If it was within 24 hours of him hearing it. No, no,
he can't, because he can't be מיפר meifer for קודמין. kodmin. So
if basically there's no father, there's קידושין, kiddushin, she makes a vow,
he can't do anything. They get married that day, he still can't
do anything because it was a vow from before נישואין, nissuin, which
again just demonstrates that his relationship with her with קידושין kiddushin really
is nothing by itself, right? Because if even if they're the only
two people in the world, no father, no whatever, whatever, and she
made it after the קידושין, kiddushin, he has no right to
annul.
רשי Rashi has some more context, exactly.
She has even more power because the father's dead and no קידושין
kiddushin yet, I guess. So anyway, but yes, that's exactly it. That
again shows how much the father is really the anchor. All right,
now, שמע בעלה והפר לה. shama baalah veheifer lah. Now this is
a little bit redundant. Again, part of this huge רן Ran is
to explain why it's telling you a חידוש, chiddush, but it's basically
redundant what we're about to
read. שמע בעלה והפר לה, shama baalah veheifer lah, the husband heard
and he
was מיפר. meifer. ולא הספיק האב לשמוע עד שמת הבעל, velo hispik
haav lishmoa ad shemet habaal, and it adds this phrase like here
in this scenario it's also telling you when did the father hear.
So the father heard it after the husband died. Anyway, it's basically
though the same point that the husband did what he needed to
do, okay, or he certainly didn't do anything problematic, and then he
died, and then the father came into the picture and only then
the father heard it. זו היא ששנינו מת הבעל נתרוקנה רשות לאב.
zo hi sheshanishnu met habaal nitrokna reshus laav. Okay, again, husband died,
he didn't make problems, father comes into the picture, whether he came
into the picture before or after doesn't matter, the father can now
annul it. Good. שמע בעלה, shama baalah, back to now the husband
hearing, I mean שמע בעלה, shama baalah, so now fourth the third
one was really a repeat. שמע בעלה, shama baalah, the husband
heard and he was מיפר, meifer, either what he needed to do.
ולא הספיק האב לשמוע עד שמת, velo hispik haav lishmoa ad shemet,
and now the father died, okay? So this is the difference. Until
now the basic case has been
A heard, did his הפרה hafara or did his קיום kiyum and
died, what is he left with? So if A is the husband,
the husband heard or whatever and he died and then the father
can't annul. If A is the father, the father heard or whatever
and he died even if he did the הפרה hafara then the
husband can't annul. Okay, so the two scenarios we've had so far
is the person who heard and did the הפרה hafara was the
one who died. Okay, those were two of the three cases two
of the two cases we've had so far. Now we're going to
get to a third case which is the opposite party that died.
Okay,
so here, husband hears, מיפר, meifer,
dies.
Okay, that was case number one, then father can annul.
Okay, he's again the anchor. If the father hears,
מיפר, meifer, dies,
husband
cannot.
Okay? So the guy who heard and did the job died, but
in this case, I mean you don't even need him to be
מיפר, meifer, you just need him to not do anything problematic.
As long as it's now going to the father we're good, but
if what's left is going to the husband we're not good. Okay,
now this case. שמע בעלה
והפר לה, shama baalah veheifer lah, the husband heard and he was
מיפר. meifer. ולא הספיק האב לשמוע עד שמת, velo hispik haav lishmoa
ad shemet,
so the husband heard,
was
מיפר, meifer, and then the father died. Okay, now you see that's
like a different scenario. Okay, this is stage one, and stage two,
the father died. So now that's a little bit different. Here it's
the question of like, I did my job, can you finish it?
Right, the father can finish it or whatever. Here the husband cannot
finish it. Because
here, I did my job, you’re not around to finish it. Okay,
I am still around, you’re not around to finish it. Can I
now finish you know can I now go ahead and finish it?
The father’s around maybe he can go ahead and just take care
of it himself. So note, that’s you know, that would be similar
to what you guys just asked about what do you call it,
about let’s say there’s no father at all? Can the husband do
it? So here there was a father then there wasn’t. Okay, can
he go ahead and finish it?
שמע אב והפר ולא הספיק הבעל לשמוע עד שמת, shama av v’heifer
v’lo hispik habaal lishmoa ad shemeit, אין הבעל יכול להפר, ein habaal
yachol l’hafer, שאין הבעל מפר אלא בשותפות. she’ein habaal meifer ela b’shutafut.
The husband needs the father’s participation. Okay, here it’s basically saying you
use the word שותפות, shutafut, but here I did what I was
supposed to do. One person was... is the other guy’s around, is
he able to finish it? Here it’s like I need the other
guy right in... right you get how here it uses the word
שותפות. shutafut. Here you have the שותפות. shutafut. It was just when
after one of the people did what they were supposed to do,
he dies. Here you don’t have the שותפות, shutafut, right? The other
guy isn’t there to do what he needs to do. And that’s
why it says this doesn’t work. The husband obviously the father doesn’t
need the שותפות shutafut of the בעל. baal. Without any בעל baal
in the picture the husband... I mean not the husband, the father
doesn’t need שותפות. shutafut. The father annuls without the husband. But the
husband, if the father isn’t around to do his thing, cannot annul.
Okay, now. שמע אביה והפר לה ולא הספיק הבעל לשמוע עד שמת.
shama aviha v’heifer lah v’lo hispik habaal lishmoa ad shemeit. Now, how
about this
case?
The father heard and... the father here heard and was
מפר meifer and then the husband dies. Now that’s right? So you
see how right? Here the guy who heard died.
He heard then he died. And then he heard and then he
died. Kind of confusing. But anyway, that’s where the dying happens. But
here the dying happens right with the other person. Okay? So those
are the two sets of cases there. Okay. So he hears and
he’s מפר meifer and then the husband dies. You would think okay
well great, right? All you really need is the father. Yeah, that’s
what we’ve been saying, all you really need is the father. It’s
a little bit different right? Because here it started that they were
in partnership. The husband was around. So maybe even though you don’t
need the husband to begin with, maybe when you have him you
need him to do his thing. Here he did his thing and
he died. You did your thing, you're died, or you didn’t do
anything problematic, I’ll take care of my thing, I’ll take care of
the rest. So here if you were never in the picture to
begin with, wonderful. But now you were in the picture and you
died. Can I go ahead and do I need to take care
of your part of it or now we can just make you
irrelevant? Okay, that’s the question of the last one. So let’s take
a look.
שמע אביה והפר לה ולא הספיק הבעל לשמוע עד שמת. shama aviha
v’heifer lah v’lo hispik habaal lishmoa ad shemeit. And the husband didn’t
hear... and the husband died and he died even without ever having
and it’s like an extreme case, he didn’t even hear it, he
just died before he knew anything. So you could argue he was
like never in the picture. Right? Never in the picture, father takes
care of it. No, here’s a debate of בית הלל בית שמאי.
Beis Hillel Beis Shammai. חוזר האב ומפר חלקו של בעל. chozer ha'av
umeifer chelko shel baal. So the first statement is the father can
go ahead and מפר meifer the portion of the husband. What’s interesting
is even this process says the father can be מפר, meifer, it
doesn’t say it just works automatically. Oh, there’s no husband, so it’s
all taken care of. Since it started and even though the husband
didn’t hear, so in some ways he wasn’t yet fully in the
picture even, since the vow was taken when there was this husband,
or I’ll call it a groom, I think it’s a bit more
precise. Since the vow started when there was this groom, there is
like a piece of it that needs to be you know annulled
that the father ends up doing on his own, okay? And therefore
even therefore when the groom dies, it’s not yet totally הופר. hufar.
There needs to have been another act of release. You know, you
could see this also just in the fact that since while the
groom was alive, the father’s הפרה hafara didn’t wasn’t effective yet. Just
because now the groom died doesn’t all of a sudden make his
הפרה hafara effective. When... like before the groom died we said the
father did the הפרה hafara and the נדר neder is still binding
until the groom died. Now the groom died, so you know, so
who's doing what the groom needed to do? Right? That’s the conceptual,
that’s the point. So it’s not that it just happens automatically when
the groom goes out of the picture. The father now does the
role of the groom, takes over the groom’s rights and annuls the
way the groom would have annulled. Okay, so that’s חוזר האב ומפר
חלקו של בעל. chozer ha'av umeifer chelko shel baal. Yes. The feature
might be that
it gives him the opportunity to change his mind.
Well,
yes, it is true that is true, he could choose not to
be מפר חלקו של בעל, meifer chelko shel baal, correct. Okay? So
even if there was no groom, he would have done it himself.
Since it started with the groom and the groom had some rights
to הפרה hafara and without his הפרה hafara it was still binding,
even then after he died, the father now takes over those rights.
Okay? אמר רבי נתן, Amar Rabi Nasan, הן הן דברי בית שמאי,
hein hein divrei Beis Shammai, no no no no no, that's בית
שמאי's Beis Shammai position, that the father goes back and takes over
the portion of the groom. אבל בית הלל, Aval Beis Hillel, בית
הלל Beis Hillel says אין יכול להפר. ein yachol lehafer. Okay,
interesting, a little reversal, right? You would always suspect that בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says, you know, בית הלל Beis Hillel giving somebody more,
you know, more rights. Gives the father more rights, giving the girl
more of an opportunity to get out of it. Okay, so here's
the reversal. According to בית הלל Beis Hillel says he cannot. If
the groom was in the picture, he had the right to do
it, he died, then nobody now takes over that right and she's
stuck. Nobody can do his role and therefore she can't get out
of it. All right?
Right? Conceptually she's not stuck, she's,
she's bound by, right, because
she made a נדר neder and they're, they're overriding her wish.
Well that's an excellent point. Maybe she wants the נדר. neder.
Right, you're right.
Maybe בית הלל's Beis Hillel being empowering of the
woman, of the girl, the girl. Okay.
Now,
what if the נדר neder had something to do with the husband?
So then what's the relevance?
Oh, you know, that is an excellent, that's an excellent point, right?
Which is according to what happens if the nature of the נדר
neder falls between, according to the רמב״ם Rambam you can't have it
fall between the cracks because the רמב״ם, Rambam, the בעל, ba'al, the
father can be מפר mefer everything and the husband only, you know,
a subset of that. But according to let's say the
ר״ן Ran of דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim shebeino leveina, you could imagine
that she takes a vow that impacts her father and not the
husband, or the husband and not the father, right? Then how does
that then play out about who could do the הפרה? hafara? That's
a great question. Like would they still be in that partnership, right?
I mean my inclination would be to say, well certainly that it
would primarily go by the father as we've been saying, but let's
say it was something that impacted her relationship with her father and
not her relationship with her husband, could the husband, would the groom
still be necessary to do the הפרה? hafara? Yeah, I don't know,
it's a really good question.
Actually I was asking, it might make the vow moot if it
has to do with the husband and then he dies. Oh.
That's, that's if it only has to do, yeah, but normally what
they're saying is it affects the husband, not that it's only about
the husband. Even if the vow was like you can't get any
הנאה hana'ah from me. Right, right, but when we normally talk about
בינו לבינה, beino leveina, it could be that but we also talk
about the impact of it affects the husband, but it's not only
directed towards the husband.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so according to
this debate of בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, what's
the debate about? So here's how the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes it and
this is how it answers its question whether when one party does
it do they cut it in half or do they weaken it?
שמע מינה לבית שמאי מיגז גייז, לבית הלל מיקלש קליש. Shma mina
leBeis Shammai migaz gayez, leBeis Hillel miklash kalish. Oh, so very clear.
What's the debate about? According to בית שמאי Beis Shammai you're cutting
it and according to בית הלל Beis Hillel you're weakening it. שמע
מינה. Shma mina. Okay, that's the conclusion. You all got that, right?
Gentlemen? Okay.
So not, I can understand it but I would have never have
come up with that.
So the point is, he had the, the בעל ba'al had his,
the father did his thing, okay. The בעל ba'al had his thing
to do and he died. Can the father take it over? So
it says like this, if you look at it as the father
did half and he had the right to annul half of the
vow, okay, and he died, torn away, the father can, that's like
a thing, right, like at the very, the concept is it's a
very concrete thing, the right to annul half of a vow, so
so that's that stuff is now taken over by the father. But
if it's that the father just weakens the vow,
so it's not like you had your piece, I have my piece
to do and I take over, right? It's like some,
right?
You're not persuaded, you're not going to be able to,
I'm not going to persuade you.
Okay, well I, I would have never have come up with that.
Well let's see the ר״ן, Ran, let's see if the ר״ן Ran
can persuade you. Okay. אבל בית הלל אומרים אין יכול להפר כלל.
Aval Beis Hillel omrim
ein yachol lehafer klal. Okay, interesting, a little reversal, it's about eight
lines up, eighth line up, at why? דאפילו חוזר ומפר חלקו וחלק
הבעל, כי היינו טעמא, משום דבית שמאי מיגז גייז קטעי. De'afilu chozer
umefer chelko vechelek haba'al, ki hainu ta'ama, mishum deBeis Shammai migaz gayez
kotei. כשהפר אב תחילה הפר חלקו בלבד. Keshehefer av techila hefer chelko
bilvad. He did his half. וחלק הבעל לא נגרע כלל. Vechelek haba'al
lo nigrah klal. And it didn't impact the husband's half, each one
of them had half, okay?
The father was annulling it for one of the olives, let's use
that example, and the, and the husband for the other olive, so
he still had his olive, each one had their olive. Okay. לא
נגרע כלל, Lo nigrah klal, אלא עדיין הוא קיים לגמרי, וחשוב הוא
להורישו לאב. ela adayin hu kayam legamrei, vechashuv hu lehorisho la'av.
So since it's something full and substantial, the power to annul the
vow on this olive, that's a full and substantial thing, that could
be transferred now to the father. ולבית הלל מיקלש קליש, UleBeis Hillel
miklash kalish, כשהפר חלקו נגרע חלקו של בעל. keshehefer chelko nigrah chelko
shel ba'al.
So when the father did it, he made the whole vow on
the two olives weaker. Okay. And now the husband is left with
like a weak vow, is what the husband is left with. ואינו
חשוב להורישו לאב, Ve'eino chashuv lehorisho la'av,
and therefore it's not so substantial, so it's only about annulling a
weak vow, so that's not something that you can transfer to somebody
else. It's not significant enough to be transferred. וכיון דאב אכתי איתיה,
Vechivan de'av akatti isei, איתיה, isei, since the father's still... Around, הפרה
דידיה לא באה לעולם, Haforoh deidei lo bo'oh l'olom, ואכתי נדרא בקלישותא
קאי, Ve'achti nidro beklishuso ko'ei, the vow is still in its weak
state, וכיון דקליש ליה כל שכן דלא מצי מוריש ליה Vekivan deklish
lei kol shekein delo matzi morish lei since it's weak so it's
all the more so that he can't transfer it. Okay, so again,
I don't know if that's persuasive or not, but there is what
you get to see here is two ideas, meaning one I think
that we can sort of identify with, and one that I think
is harder to identify with. One we can identify with is that
it uses this phrase of להוריש, lehorish, and that's a phrase that
the גמרא Gemara does use. Here it's not talking about a physical
object. It's talking about a right. The גמרא Gemara very often uses
the phrase about that, particularly when talking about the father and his
daughter, whether he transfers his rights to the sons when he dies
and so on, if he מוריש זכותא דאב לברי, morish zchuta de'av
livrei, you know, if he מוריש morish it to his sons.
So are you, can you transfer the rights that you have to
do this type of a thing? So that's I think okay, fine,
that's one way of conceptualizing it. If he dies, does that power
transfer to the father? Okay, but the question then being that if
it's a weaker power, it's not significant enough, if you sort of
say that since we're using the model of ירושה, yerusha, we have
to think about it as a type of an object. So if
you have to think about it as a type of an object,
you have to think about it as something substantial. So if it's
something that you've got full power to do this on behalf of
the thing, but it's still substantial, it's a half a loaf, it's
still a loaf, it's still a real piece of bread, so you
can conceptualize it like an object and say it could be transferred.
But if it's something that's very weak, okay, then it's not so
substantive that we can't conceptually use the idea that something that could
be bequeathed or transferred or whatever. So it seems to be that's
the model here. A, introducing a model of ירושה, yerusha, and B,
with that model, something has to be object-like or significant that this
abstract thing becomes some type of a thing that can be transferred
and therefore if it's weak it cannot. All right, so we will
end with that today, nice and early.
Yeah.
I like the bank account analogy. If it's a joint account
if...